A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Office Files of Robert Curvin FA626
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Office Files of Robert Curvin
1981-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Curvin, Robert
Ford Foundation
FA626
5 Cubic Feet
The Office Files of Robert Curvin document planning, implementation and management of grants by the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty Program during the period 1981-1996. There are substantial files relating to Foundation support for community development corporations, response to the Los Angeles riots of 1991 and the work of other foundations on such urban issues as housing, education, substance abuse and employment. The files contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, grant proposals and meeting materials. They are arranged in a single alphabetical series. The collection measures 5 linear feet and is contained in 5 record cartons.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Biographical Note
Robert Curvin joined the Ford Foundation in 1988 as Director of the Urban Poverty Program (UPP), which under his leadership granted over $50 million annually to revitalize neighborhoods and expand economic opportunities for city residents. In 1996, Curvin was appointed VicePresident for Communications. Curvin retired from the Ford Foundation in January 2000, and later served as President of the Greentree Foundation. Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, he served for five years as Dean of the Graduate School of Urban and Public Policy at the New School for Social Research in New York City. He also spent six years as a member of the Editorial Board of The New York Times, where he wrote on a wide range of social policy issues. From 1960-1970 he was a social worker in New York City and New Jersey, and from 1974-1978 taught politics at Brooklyn college. He holds a B.A. (1960) and M.A. (1964) in social work from Rutgers University, and a Ph.D. (1975) in political science from Princeton University.
Organizational History
Ford Foundation support for an array of programs to alleviate urban poverty in the United States dates from the 1960s, when funding was provided to the Gray Areas program – a model for later federal programs associated with the War on Poverty – and to the first wave of community development corporations. In 1981, as part of a major institutional reorganization, the Foundation established its Urban Poverty Program (UPP). UPP encompassed existing grant portfolios for urban affairs, community development, employment and job training, welfare, teen pregnancy, crime, pre-college education and population. Bernard McDonald served as UPP Director from 1981-1987. The principal institutions that UPP assisted during the 1980s were community development corporations, human service organizations and public secondary schools. Under Robert Curvin's leadership from 1988-1996, UPP expanded its commitment to grantmaking aimed at issues relating to housing, substance abuse and urban poverty outside of the United States.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Robert Curvin document strategic planning and grantmaking by the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty Program during the period 1981-1996. There are substantial files relating to the work of Ford-funded community development corporations, Foundation response to the Los Angeles riots of 1991, the federal government's Empowerment Zone initiative, and the work of other foundations on various urban issues. Files on "Miami Staff Conference on Urban Initiatives," "Program Review," and "Reichmann, Rebecca" are especially rich in material concerning UPP strategy and program development. The transcript of a 1990 interview of Curvin and Program Officer Prudence Brown provides useful context and background on UPP work during the 1980s (Box 3, Folder 19). Files concerning the work of Foundation Program Officers (Roland Anglin, Prudence Brown, et al) contain a variety of documents related to grants and initiatives coordinated by these individuals. The files contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, grant proposals and meeting materials, and are arranged in a single alphabetical series. The collection measures 5 linear feet and is contained in 5 record cartons.
Arrangement
The Urban Poverty Program Files of Robert Curvin are arranged alphabetically.
Separated Materials
Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from the papers and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. A list of the titles of these reports is appended to this register.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
- Amelior Foundation, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
- America in the 21st Century, 1989 (Box 1)
- American Association of State Colleges and Universities, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
- Andrews, Nancy O. -- Memorandum re: Housing, 1989 (Box 1)
- Anglin, Roland, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
- Applied Research Center, 1993 (Box 1)
- Arrick, Ellen, 1994 (Box 1)
- Association of Black Foundation Executives, 1987-1993 (Box 1)
- Atlanta, Corporation for Olympic Development in, 1994 (Box 1)
- Bailey, Charles R. -- Memorandum re: Grant to Proshika Manobik Unnayan Kendra, 1989 (Box 1)
- Bermudez, Diana -- Memoranda re: Community Development Corporations, 1988-1993 (Box 1)
- Birla, Ritu, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
- Board of Trustees -- Meetings, 1991-1995 (Box 1)
- Board of Trustees -- Urban Poverty Program Reserve Requests, 1996 (Box 1)
- Brown, Ellen, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
- Brown, O. Chance, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
- Brown, Prue, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
- Buhl and Associates, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
- Business Executives for National Security, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
- Business Loans to Minority-Led Businesses, 1992 (Box 1)
- Carter Center, 1992 (Box 1)
- Cathedral of St. John the Divine, 1988 (Box 1)
- Center for Educational Innovation, 1991 (Box 1)
- Center for Urban Policy Research, 1988-1991 (Box 1)
- Chavis, David, 1989 (Box 1)
- Chen, Ellen E., 1993 (Box 1)
- Chile, 1993 (Box 1)
- China, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
- Churches as Agents of Community Economic Development, 1989 (Box 1)
- Citizens Commission on AIDS (5 folders), 1988-1990 (Box 1)
- Community Development Corporations and the Arts (2 folders), 1990-1993 (Box 1)
- Community Development Corporations and Child Care, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
- Community Development Corporation and Civil Rights, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
- Community Development Corporations Conference -- Puerto Rico, 1995 (Box 1)
- Community Development Corporations -- Human Rights Issues, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
- Community Development Corporations -- Miscellaneous, 1991; n.d. (Box 1)
- Community Development Finance Initiative, 1995 (Box 1)
- Community Development Partnerships, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
- Conrad H. Hilton Foundation, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
- Conservation Company, 1990 (Box 1)
- Corporation for Supportive Housing, 1992 (Box 1)
- Coward, E. Walter, 1992 (Box 1)
- Dassin, Joan -- Brazil and Latin America Grants, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
- DeGiovanni, Frank -- Program Related Investments, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Designwrights Collaborative, Inc., 1991 (Box 2)
- Development Banking, 1992 (Box 2)
- Diaz, William A. -- Puerto Rico and Latino Grants, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
- Diversity Initiative, 1991 (Box 2)
- Domestic Policy Agenda, 1992 (Box 2)
- Drug Policy Foundation, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
- East St. Louis (4 folders), 1990-1995 (Box 2)
- Education and Urban Poverty Staff Retreat, 1994 (Box 2)
- Educational Policy, undated (Box 2)
- El-Koly, Heba -- Cairo Office, 1991-1993 (Box 2)
- Elliott, Mark (2 folders), 1991-1995 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone (2 folders), 1993-1995 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- Austin Application, 1994 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- Boston, 1995 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- Harlem Urban Development Corporation, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- Monitoring and Assistance Project -- Columbia University, 1994-1996 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- New York City Application, 199 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- New York City Application Drafts, 1994 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- New York City Letters of Support, 1994 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- Philanthropic Involvement Meeting, 1995 (Box 2)
- Empowerment Zone -- Project Summaries, undated (Box 2)
- English, John W. -- China Trip, 1990 (Box 2)
- Fannie Mae Foundation, 1990-1993 (Box 2)
- Flynn, Christine and Mister, Melvin -- Community Development Corporation Intermediaries Consultancy, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
- Fordham University, 1992 (Box 2)
- 42nd Street Light Rail Transit, 1994 (Box 2)
- Foundation Executives Education Reform Group, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
- Foundation for American Communications, 1991 (Box 3)
- Fulbright, Karen -- Youth Programs, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
- Gaberman, Barry D., 1987 (Box 3)
- Georgia Pacific Corporation, 1988 (Box 3)
- Gerdes, Gina, 1988 (Box 3)
- Ginzberg, Eli, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
- Greater Cleveland Roundtable, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
- Halpern, Robert, 1986-1993 (Box 3)
- Historically Black Colleges and Community Development, 1989 (Box 3)
- Homosexual Equal Rights, 1993 (Box 3)
- Housing Leadership Development for Minorities and Women, 1989 (Box 3)
- Hughes, Mark Alan, 1993 (Box 3)
- Hurricane Andrew, 1991 (Box 3)
- International Center for Research on Women, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
- Jackson, Peter, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
- Jhally, Sut, 1993 (Box 3)
- Johnson Foundation, 1989 (Box 3)
- Kahn, Carol, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
- Katz, Michael -- Transcript of Interview of Robert Curvin and Prue Brown, 1990 (Box 3)
- Kellogg Foundation, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
- Koprowski, John, 1993 (Box 3)
- Kubisch, Anne C., 1991-1994 (Box 3)
- Lanigan, John, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
- Latin America Regional Meeting, 1992 (Box 3)
- Lilly Endowment, Inc., 1989-1991 (Box 3)
- Lipsky, Michael, 1991-1995 (Box 3)
- Literacy, 1992-1995 (Box 3)
- Livelihood, Employment and Income Generation, 1989-1994 (Box 3)
- Los Angeles Collaboration for Community Development, 1990-1995 (Box 3)
- Los Angeles Task Force (4 folders), 1992-1994 (Box 3)
- Lynch, Barbara -- Caribbean Programs, 1992-1994 (Box 3)
- Martin and Glantz -- Urban Poverty Program Communications Strategy, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
- Mary Brown Productions, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
- Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), 1988 (Box 3)
- Mature Community Development Corporation Initiative -- Budget and RGA's, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
- Mature Community Development Corporation Initiative -- Grantees, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
- Mature Community Development Corporation Initiative -- Meetings (2 folders), 1990-1994 (Box 3)
- Miami Community Development Corporation (2 folders), 1988 (Box 4)
- Miami Staff Conference on Urban Initiatives, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
- Miami Staff Conference on Urban Initiatives -- Transcripts, 1989 (Box 4)
- Miami Survey, 1990 (Box 4)
- Miller, Tom, 1990-1994 (Box 4)
- Mincy, Ronald B., 1994-1995 (Box 4)
- Minority Economic Development, 1988 (Box 4)
- Mohamed, Inca A. -- Youth Development Program, 1995 (Box 4)
- Molnar, Janice, 1992-1994 (Box 4)
- Nadelman, Ethan A. -- Drug Policy, 1988-1995 (Box 4)
- Nairobi Office, 1988-1993 (Box 4)
- National Affairs -- Civil Rights Program, 1981 (Box 4)
- National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1988-1993 (Box 4)
- National Civic League, 1992 (Box 4)
- National Community Development Initiative (3 folders), 1988-1995 (Box 4)
- National Puerto Rican Coalition, 1988 (Box 4)
- National Service, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
- National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1988-1995 (Box 4)
- National Urban League, 1995 (Box 4)
- Nelson A Rockefeller Institute of Government, 1993 (Box 4)
- New York City Partnership, Inc., 1988-1994 (Box 4)
- New York Foundation Executives Group (2 folders), 1991-1993 (Box 4)
- New York Urban Coalition, Inc., 1989 (Box 4)
- NHP Foundation, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
- O'Connor, Alice -- Public Service Program Strategies, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
- Offenheiser, Raymond, 1994 (Box 4)
- Page, Chris, 1993-1995 (Box 4)
- Pew Charitable Trusts, 1989-1994 (Box 4)
- Philadelphia Community Development, 1988 (Box 4)
- Philadelphia Neighborhood Development Corporation, 1988 (Box 4)
- Philanthropy and Public Policy, 1989 (Box 4)
- Philippines (2 folders), 1993-1994 (Box 4)
- Philippines, 1995 (Box 5)
- Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, 1989 (Box 5)
- Poston, Richard W -- Southern Illinois University, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
- Pratt Institute Center for Community and Environmental Development, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
- Program Related Investments (PRI), 1990-1995 (Box 5)
- Program Review (3 folders), 1989-1993 (Box 5)
- Project Redirection, 1992 (Box 5)
- Race Relations, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
- Rand Visit, 1991 (Box 5)
- Reichman, Rebecca -- Urban Poverty Program Strategy, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
- Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
- Roman, Ruth, 1994 (Box 5)
- Rural Poverty and Resources, 1991-1993 (Box 5)
- Russell Sage Foundation, 1991 (Box 5)
- Sanborn, Cynthia -- Latin America Programs, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
- Schwarz, Marian L. (2 folders), 1991-1994 (Box 5)
- Sexuality, 1992 (Box 5)
- Smith, Peter, 1992 (Box 5)
- Social Capital, 1993 (Box 5)
- Solarz, Stephen J., 1988 (Box 5)
- South Africa, 1988-1994 (Box 5)
- South Bronx Site Visits, 1989-1994 (Box 5)
- Southwest Initiative, 1992-1994 (Box 5)
- Special Needs Housing, 1991 (Box 5)
- Spencer, Edson W., 1989-1992 (Box 5)
- Substance Abuse Initiative, 1990 (Box 5)
- Taylor, Andrea -- Media Grants, 1988-1995 (Box 5)
- United States Department of Housing and Urban Development, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
- Urban Assembly, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
- Urban Institute, 1990 (Box 5)
- Urban Opportunity Program, 1990 (Box 5)
- Urban Poverty Program Staff Retreats, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
- Urban Poverty Program -- Worldwide, 1988-1994 (Box 5)
- Urban Summit, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
- Violence in the Urban Environment, 1993 (Box 5)
- Vincent, Christine -- Arts and Culture Grants, 1992-1994 (Box 5)
- Violence Prevention, 1992-1994 (Box 5)
- Visiting Scholars, 1991 (Box 5)
- Winnick, Lou -- Immigration Proposal, 1989 (Box 5)
- Women and Development, 1989 (Box 5)
- Women in Community Development, 1995 (Box 5)
- World Vision, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
- Worldwide Development Organizations, 1994 (Box 5)
- Yogi Bear Sunday School, 1989 (Box 5)
- Young Minority Males at Risk, 1989 (Box 5)